A Guide to the Records of the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals, 1871-1914
Library of Virginia
Library of Virginia
Records of the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals, 1871-1914
The Library of Virginia
31211
3.6 cu. ft. (8 boxes)
Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals
Administrative Information
Access Restrictions
There are no restrictions.
Acquisition Information
Transferred by Allen L. Lucy, Clerk, Supreme Court of Virginia, Richmond, Virginia. 26 September 1981.
Historical Information
The Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals was created by an act of the General Assembly passed at the May 1779 session and has continued to the present day. Its antecedent was the General Court, which, after it was reestablished under the constitution of 1776, shared appellate jurisdiction with the Supreme Court until 1851, when the new state constitution abolished the General Court. Prior to that date, the General Court had criminal jurisdiction, while the Supreme Court was restricted to civil cases. While the court now has concurrent original jurisdiction in issuing and hearing writs of habeas corpus, mandamus and prohibition, retirement, removal, and matters of judicial censure, its jurisdiction is almost exclusively appellate. An act of the General Assembly passed on March 16, 1971 changed the name of the court to the Supreme Court of Virginia.
Originally, the judges of the other state courts also served on the Supreme Court. However, since 1789 Supreme Court judges have been elected by the General Assembly. Currently the court has seven justices whose term in office is twelve years. Although the Supreme Court has always held its sessions in Richmond, it also has met from time to time in other locations in the state for the convenience of its litigants. In particular, the court met at Wytheville from 1870-1945 and at Staunton from 1870-1971.
Scope and Content
Contains a variety of material including correspondence, job applications and recommendations, court case papers, law license applications, completed Bar Examinations, as well as proposals, bids and receipts for printing from the office of the Clerk of Court. The material reveals the process by which citizens were appointed to positions within the Court, as well the steps lawyers had to take in order to become licensed to practice in Virginia. Documents found in this collection also show the process by which printing of the Court's records was procured and managed by the Clerk of Court.
Arrangement
This collection is arranged into the following series:
Series I. Correspondence, 1882-1910
Series II. Court Papers and Miscellaneous Documents, 1871-1914
Series III. Law License Applications and Bar Examinations, 1898-1906
Series IV. Printing Records, 1880-1903
Contents List
- Series I. Correspondence, 1882-1910. (Box 1-4.)
  Contains mostly correspondence related to filling vacancies at the various courts. The positions applied for include clerk, crier, librarian, reporter, stenographer, and tipstaff. The vacancies were spread amongst the courts at Richmond, Staunton and Wytheville. Most applicants wrote letters their own letters to the Supreme Court justices, but letters of recommendation and endorsement from prominent citizens were submitted as well. In many cases, an applicant's folder contains several copies of the same letter sent to each justice. Almost all of the application correspondence dates from the same time period (1894-1895). Also found in this series are two folders of letters written upon the death of Judge R.C.L. Moncure in 1882, and one folder of miscellaneous correspondence.
  The application material is arranged according to the position applied for, and then grouped alphabetically by the last name of the applicant. The additional folders of general correspondence can be found at the end of the list.
  - Clerk of Court, Richmond.
    - Taylor, George K., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 1)
  - Clerk of Court, Staunton.
    - Barnes, C.S.W., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 2)
    - Boude, John C., 1894-1895. (Box 1, Folder 3)
    - Kinney, John M., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 4)
    - Kinney, John M., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 5)
    - Powell, John A., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Shenard, J.H., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 6)
    - Waddell, Joseph A., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 7)
  - Clerk of Court, Wytheville.
    - Campbell, A.A., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 8)
    - Fudge, G.H., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 9)
    - Lowry, William G.G., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 10)
    - Lowry, William G.G., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 11)
    - Lowry, William G.G., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 12)
    - Lowry, William G.G., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 13)
    - Lowry, William G.G., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 14)
    - Lynch, T.A., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Morriss, M.M., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 15)
    - Pendleton, William C., 1894. (Box 1, Folder 16)
    - Powell, John J.A., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 1)
    - Powell, John J.A., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 2)
    - Powell, John J.A., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 3)
    - Talliaferro, Van, 1894. (Box 2, Folder 4)
    - Terry, F.H., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 5)
    - Terry, F.H., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 6)
    - Terry, F.H., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 7)
    - Thomas, C.B., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 8)
    - Unidentified endorsement letter, 1894. (Box 2, Folder 8)
  - Crier.
    - Cook, John A., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 9)
    - Cook, John A., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 10)
  - Librarian.
    - Christian, Joseph, 1894. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Cooper, Charles W., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 11)
    - Fauntleroy, Randolph, 1894. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Hawkins, John B., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 12)
    - Micou, A.R., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 13)
    - Minor, Benjamin B., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Montiero, J.X., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 14)
    - Quarles, John E., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Sanders, J.A., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 15)
    - Scott, W.W., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 16)
    - Scott, W.W., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 17)
    - Scott, W.W., 1894. (Box 2, Folder 18)
    - Turner, Charles W., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 1)
    - Turner, Charles W., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 2)
    - Van Doren, William, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Wysor, B.J., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 3)
    - Richards, L.M., 1910. (Box 3, Folder 4)
    - Turner, Charles, 1910. (Box 3, Folder 4)
  - Librarian / Crier.
    - Talliaferro, William M., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 5)
  - Reporter.
    - Brown, Edward, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 6)
    - Brown, J. Thompson, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 7)
    - Brown, J. Thompson, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 8)
    - Burks, Martin P., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Davies, Samuel D., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 9)
    - Eby, Abram C., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Grattan, George, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 10)
    - Harrison, James P., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 11)
    - Howard, Overton, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 12)
    - Howard, Overton, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 13)
    - Kirkpatrick, F.S., 1894-1895. (Box 3, Folder 14)
    - Logan, R.H., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Matthews, James M., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 15)
    - Moncure, E.C., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 16)
    - Moore, Samuel J.C., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 17)
    - Moore, Samuel J.C., 1894. (Box 3, Folder 18)
    - Saunders, Edward, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 19)
    - Saunders, Edward, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 20)
    - Saunders, Edward, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 21)
    - Scott, R. Carter, 1894. (Box 3, Folder 22)
    - Tredway, James L., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 1)
    - Tredway, James L., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 2)
    - Tredway, James L., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 3)
    - Turner, C.W., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 4)
    - Turner, Robert H., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 4)
  - Stenographer.
    - Bolling, John R., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 5)
    - Jones, Stewart, 1894. (Box 4, Folder 5)
  - Tipstaff, Richmond.
    - Bigger, Samuel W., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 6)
    - Burgess, D.M., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 7)
    - Gaulding, R.J., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 8)
    - Hackett, Samuel P., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 9)
    - Moncure, W. Eustace, 1894. (Box 4, Folder 10)
    - Russell, W.E., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 11)
    - Talley, John L., 1894-1895. (Box 4, Folder 12)
    - Ward, Robert D., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 13)
  - Tipstaff / Crier, Richmond.
    - Hulce, Herbert L., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 12)
  - Tipstaff, Staunton.
    - Kinney, William N., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 14)
    - Turner, Logan, 1894. (Box 4, Folder 15)
  - Tipstaff, Wytheville.
    - Cook, John A., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 16)
  - Tipstaff / Crier / Janitor, Wytheville.
    - Gibson, Peter, 1894. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Harper, John E., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Hockett, J.C., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Houston, M.D., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Moyers, David H., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Romans, John M., Jr., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 17)
    - Wolfe, W.A., 1894. (Box 4, Folder 17)
  - Miscellaneous Correspondence.
    - Application envelopes and lists, 1894; undated. (Box 4, Folder 18)
    - Death of Judge R.C.L. Moncure (Memorial Meeting), 1882. (Box 4, Folder 19)
    - Death of Judge R.C.L. Moncure (Memorial Meeting), 1882. (Box 4, Folder 20)
    - Miscellaneous letters, 1886-1896. (Box 4, Folder 21)
- Series II. Court Papers and Miscellaneous Documents, 1871-1914. (Box 5.)
  Contains papers associated with a variety of court cases assumed to have been heard by the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals. Some of the papers are arranged according to the style of suit. Other court papers, mostly court orders from the Staunton and Wytheville courts, were found to be grouped together according to the court in which they were heard. That original arrangement was maintained. Also included in this series is a group of miscellaneous court-related documents and reference material, such as the signed oath of Judge Martin P. Burks (1919), and a published version of the Rules of the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals (1871).
  Arranged in three groups: court papers by style of suit, court papers by court, and miscellaneous/reference material. Arranged alphabetically within.
  - Papers by Style of Suit.
    - Administrator of Richard Baugham vs New York, Philadelphia and Norfolk Railroad, 1914. (Box 5, Folder 1)
    - Bridgewater Roller Mills Company vs Strough, 1901. (Box 5, Folder 2)
    - Broaddus, et. al. vs Supervisors of Essex County, 1901. (Box 5, Folder 3)
    - John H. Core vs City of Norfolk, 1901. (Box 5, Folder 4)
    - Fidelity Loan and Trust Company vs John Engleby, et. al., 1900. (Box 5, Folder 5)
    - First National Bank of Roanoke vs Terry's Administrator, 1900. (Box 5, Folder 6)
    - Hancock vs White-Hall Tobacco Warehouse, 1902. (Box 5, Folder 7)
    - Hancock vs White-Hall Tobacco Warehouse, 1902. (Box 5, Folder 8)
    - Raymond Hudson vs T.J. Barham, Trustee, undated. (Box 5, Folder 9)
    - William M. McAllister vs Lewis Harman and Carter Berkeley, 1901. (Box 5, Folder 10)
    - Millhiser Manufacturing vs Gallego Mills Company, et. al., undated. (Box 5, Folder 11)
    - William O'Boyle vs Commonwealth of Virginia, 1901. (Box 5, Folder 12)
    - Richmond, Fredericksburg and Potomac Railroad Company vs Johnston, et. al., 1901. (Box 5, Folder 13)
    - Amelia Russell vs Commonwealth of Virginia, undated. (Box 5, Folder 14)
    - Charles Shoemaker vs Joseph M. Bowman, undated. (Box 5, Folder 15)
    - F.C. Todd vs Charles L. Ruffin, et. al., 1902. (Box 5, Folder 16)
    - Virginia Coal and Coke Company vs Judge William S. Stuart, 1902. (Box 5, Folder 17)
  - Papers by Court.
    - Staunton, 1880. (Box 5, Folder 18)
    - Staunton, 1893. (Box 5, Folder 19)
    - Staunton, 1894. (Box 5, Folder 20)
    - Wytheville, 1880. (Box 5, Folder 21)
    - Wytheville, 1893 June. (Box 5, Folder 22)
    - Wytheville, 1893 July. (Box 5, Folder 23)
    - Wytheville, 1894. (Box 5, Folder 24)
    - Wytheville, 1894. (Box 5, Folder 25)
  - Miscellaneous Documents / Reference Material.
    - Argument Docket, Supreme Court of Appeals of West Virginia, 1904. (Box 5, Folder 26)
    - Court fee receipts, 1879-1886. (Box 5, Folder 27)
    - Oath: Judge Martin P. Burks, 1919. (Box 5, Folder 28)
    - Oath: Andrew C. Gilligan, 1900. (Box 5, Folder 29)
    - Rules of the Supreme Court of Porto Rico, 1904. (Box 5, Folder 30)
    - Rules of the Virginia Supreme Court of Appeals, 1871. (Box 5, Folder 31)
- Series III. Law License Applications and Bar Examinations, 1898-1906. (Box 6-7.)
  Contains applications for certification to take the Bar Examination, as well as handwritten exams. During this time, applicants were required to apply for certification through the Court before taking the exam. Each applicant was also required to submit written recommendations from practicing lawyers regarding the applicant's knowledge and character. Along with the applications is one folder of related correspondence. This series also contains many completed, handwritten examinations, all of which received failing grades. The examinations include both the questions and the answers given. Many of the exams are undated.
  Applications are arranged alphabetically by applicant's last name, while the examinations are arranged chronologically by year, and then alphabetically within.
  - Law License Applications.
    - Archer, Henry F., 1898. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Armistead, Frank, 1899. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Aylett, P.H., 1899. (Box 6, Folder 1)
    - Bolling, Frank C., 1899. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Brown, Gordon, 1899. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Dame, Charles M., 1899. (Box 6, Folder 2)
    - Goodwyn, H.W., 1899. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Guerrant, John G., 1898. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - Hobson, Haskins, Jr., 1899. (Box 6, Folder 3)
    - McCormick, Frank, 1899. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Mooklar, W. Temple, 1898-1899. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Moore, Robert E., 1899. (Box 6, Folder 4)
    - Rives, Robert S., 1898. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Ross, John, Jr., 1899. (Box 6, Folder 5)
    - Weckert, John C., 1899. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Weymouth, John, 1899. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - Welsh, John B., 1899. (Box 6, Folder 6)
    - White, David M., 1899. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Williams, R. Gray, 1899. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Winn, Arthur W., 1899. (Box 6, Folder 7)
    - Application-related correspondence, 1900. (Box 6, Folder 8)
  - Bar Examinations (Failed).
    - 1903.
      - Burdett, Lewis S. (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Pearson, Harry L. (Box 6, Folder 9)
      - Stoakley, W.D. (Box 6, Folder 9)
    - 1904.
      - Beverly, L.T. (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - French, Killey S. (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Harris, Thomas S. (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Lewis, James T. (Box 6, Folder 10)
      - Pearson, Harry L. (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Sutherland, M.L. (Box 6, Folder 11)
      - Stoakley, W.D. (Box 6, Folder 11)
    - 1905.
      - Bragg, Sanford B. (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Cutchins, John A. (Box 6, Folder 12)
      - Daugherty, W.A. (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Harris, T.S. (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Hulton, A.P. (Box 6, Folder 13)
      - Leonard, James H. (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Light, S.H. (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Reid, Joseph H. (Box 6, Folder 14)
      - Sutherland, M.L. (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Whitley, George F. (Box 6, Folder 15)
      - Williamson, J.L. (Box 6, Folder 16)
      - Wilson, Charles G. (Box 6, Folder 16)
    - 1906.
      - Baggarly, F.C. (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Beverly, F.T. (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Bickers, H.C. (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Jackson, William. (Box 7, Folder 1)
      - Liggan, William G. (Box 7, Folder 1)
    - Undated.
      - Armistead, Frank. (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Bowlin, W.B. (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Crockett, Albert P. (Box 7, Folder 2)
      - Duff, Thomas F. (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Issacs, George G. (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Lewis, James T. (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Peatross, [Illegible]. (Box 7, Folder 3)
      - Thomas, S.B. (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Thraves, W.V. (Box 7, Folder 4)
      - Tucker, Grafton. (Box 7, Folder 4)
- Series IV. Printing Records, 1880-1903. (Box 7-8.)
  Contains a variety of documents related to the printing of court records by the Clerk of the Supreme Court of Appeals. It appears that the Court was required to solicit bids for printing every year through a newspaper advertisement. The company with the most attractive bid was then responsible for printing the Court's records for the following year. Included in this series are printing account payment receipts, proposals and bids submitted by printers, very limited correspondence, and two General Assembly bills related to changes to the Code of Virginia affecting the Clerk and the printing of court records.
  Arranged alphabetically according to type of record; arrangement within each group varies.
  - Printing Accounts Paid.
    - 1880-1881. (Box 7, Folder 5)
    - 1881. (Box 7, Folder 6)
    - 1882-1883. (Box 7, Folder 7)
    - 1883-1884. (Box 7, Folder 8)
    - 1884-1885. (Box 7, Folder 9)
    - 1885-1886. (Box 7, Folder 10)
    - 1886-1887. (Box 7, Folder 11)
    - 1887-1888. (Box 7, Folder 12)
    - 1888-1889. (Box 7, Folder 13)
    - 1894. (Box 7, Folder 14)
    - 1894-1895. (Box 7, Folder 15)
    - 1895-1896. (Box 7, Folder 16)
    - 1896-1897. (Box 7, Folder 17)
    - 1897-1898. (Box 7, Folder 18)
    - 1898-1899. (Box 7, Folder 19)
    - 1899-1900. (Box 7, Folder 20)
    - 1900-1901. (Box 7, Folder 21)
    - 1901-1902. (Box 8, Folder 1)
    - 1902-1903. (Box 8, Folder 2)
    - undated. (Box 8, Folder 3)
    - Lists of Cases and Amounts for Printing Records, 1894-1898. (Box 8, Folder 4)
  - Printing Proposals.
    - 1882. (Box 8, Folder 5)
    - 1883-1884. (Box 8, Folder 6)
    - 1885-1886. (Box 8, Folder 7)
    - 1887-1888. (Box 8, Folder 8)
    - 1888-1889. (Box 8, Folder 9)
    - 1889-1890. (Box 8, Folder 10)
    - 1890-1891. (Box 8, Folder 11)
    - 1891-1892. (Box 8, Folder 12)
    - 1892-1893. (Box 8, Folder 13)
    - 1893-1894. (Box 8, Folder 14)
    - 1894-1895. (Box 8, Folder 15)
    - 1895. (Box 8, Folder 16)
    - 1896-1897. (Box 8, Folder 17)
    - 1898-1899. (Box 8, Folder 18)
    - 1899-1900. (Box 8, Folder 19)
    - 1900. (Box 8, Folder 20)
    - 1901. (Box 8, Folder 21)
    - 1902-1903. (Box 8, Folder 22)
    - 1903. (Box 8, Folder 23)
  - Printing-Related Documents.
    - Correspondence, 1892-1902. (Box 8, Folder 24)
    - General Assembly Bill to Amend and Reenact Section 3476 of the Code of Virginia, undated. (Box 8, Folder 25)
    - General Assembly Bill to Amend and Reenact Section 3507 of the Code of Virginia, undated. (Box 8, Folder 26)
    - Response to General Assembly Proposed Code Changes, undated. (Box 8, Folder 27)